BANK OF <Location gate:gateId="1542" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">AMERICA</Location> SEES SLOW <Location gate:gateId="1543" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1484;1485;1498;1518">U.S.</Location> CONSUMER SPENDING
  A trade-led boom in the <Location gate:gateId="1545" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1484;1485;1498;1518">U.S.</Location> is
  unlikely this year or next because growth in net exports will
  merely offset a dramatic slowdown in consumer spending and
  other sectors of the economy, <Organization gate:gateId="1547" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1487;1494;1507">Bank of America</Organization> said in its
  latest economic report.
      Although net exports will add 0.7 pct to GNP this year,
  after reducing it by 1.2 pct in 1986, consumer spending will
  contribute 1.4 pct less to GNP than it did last year.
      As a result, GNP this year is likely to expand a modest 2.5
  pct, the same rate as last year, according to <Person gate:gateId="1548" firstName="Daniel" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Dyke" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="1493;1497;1510;1517">Daniel Van Dyke</Person>,
  the <Organization gate:gateId="1549" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1487;1494;1507">Bank of America</Organization> economist who wrote the report.
      &quot;Growth in consumer spending in the <Location gate:gateId="1550" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">United States</Location> will drop
  dramatically this year because the jump in inflation will cause
  a falloff in the growth of disposable income,&quot; <Person gate:gateId="1551" firstName="Van" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Dyke" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="1493;1497;1510;1517">Van Dyke</Person> said.
      Growth in <Location gate:gateId="1552" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1484;1485;1498;1518" kind="locName">U.S.</Location> consumer spending is likely to slow to 1.8
  pct this year from 4.1 pct in 1986, he predicted.
      The report was released before the <Organization gate:gateId="1553" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Commerce Department</Organization>
  reported today that personal income rose just 0.2 pct in May,
  after increasing 0.4 pct in April, and that personal
  consumption expenditures had risen just 0.1 pct, compared with
  a 0.6 pct increase the month before.
      The rising cost of energy and imports is likely to boost
  consumer prices by an average of 3.7 pct this year, up from 1.9
  pct in 1986, <Organization gate:gateId="1540" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1487;1494;1507">Bank of America</Organization> forecast.
      This rise in inflation will reduce real disposable income 
  growth to only 1.3 pct in 1987 from 2.9 pct in 1986.
      As a result, <Person gate:gateId="1541" firstName="Van" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Dyke" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="1493;1497;1510;1517">Van Dyke</Person> calculated that the purchasing power
  of an average family of four will increase by a modest 540 dlrs
  this year compared to a surge of 1,210 dlrs during 1986.
      The slowdown in income growth is likely to cause housing
  starts to drop by 4.2 pct this year and a further six pct in
  1988 to an annual rate of 1.63 mln units.
      &quot;For the first time in several years, a recession in 1988
  or 1989 is more than a remote possibility,&quot; <Person gate:gateId="1544" firstName="Van" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Dyke" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="1493;1497;1510;1517">Van Dyke</Person> said.
      Currently, <Location gate:gateId="1546" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1484;1485;1498;1518">U.S.</Location> growth is fragile and depends heavily on an
  improvement in trade. &quot;However, with protectionist attitudes on
  the rise in this country, this source of growth is at risk,&quot; he
  added.
  

