World pole vault champion <Person gate:gateId="1088" rule="PersonJobTitle" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gate:matches="1057;1081;1082;1083;1084;1085;1086;1087" kind="fullName">Shawn Barber</Person> avoided a two-year suspension for an anti-doping violation after inadvertently ingesting cocaine when kissing a woman he met on the internet. The athlete was permitted to compete at the Olympic Games in <Location gate:gateId="1089" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="1058;1059" kind="locName">Rio</Location>, despite testing positive for the drug. <Person gate:gateId="1095" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1057;1081;1082;1083;1084;1085;1086;1087" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Barber</Person> was spared a ban after successfully arguing that the drug had been passed on through “kissing”. An independent arbitrator ruled “no fault or negligence” by <Person gate:gateId="1096" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1057;1081;1082;1083;1084;1085;1086;1087" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Barber</Person>, who finished 10th in <Location gate:gateId="1090" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="1058;1059" kind="locName">Rio</Location>. Athletics <Location gate:gateId="1091" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1060;1065">Canada</Location> called the decision “fair and reasonable”. <Person gate:gateId="1097" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1057;1081;1082;1083;1084;1085;1086;1087" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Barber</Person> posted an online advert on Craiglist asking for a “sexual encounter of some sort” with a woman who was “drug and disease free”. The athlete admitted that he sought a “way to relieve stress” ahead of the Canadian Olympic trials. The woman involved in the encounter said she had consumed cocaine but did not inform <Person gate:gateId="1098" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1057;1081;1082;1083;1084;1085;1086;1087" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Barber</Person> she had taken the drug before going on to repeatedly kiss him. Authorities published the decision, which was made on August 11, on Thursday. <Person gate:gateId="1094" matchedWithLonger="true" rule="PersonSays" gate:matches="1057;1081;1082;1083;1084;1085;1086;1087">Barber</Person> said in a statement: &quot;I am obviously satisfied with the result of the hearing where I was found to have zero fault. &quot;I am happy to have this behind me so that I can move on with my career with a free conscience. &quot;At no time during my actions, did I even fathom the possibility of being able to be contaminated with cocaine. This is a learning experience that I hope other athletes can learn from as I have.&quot; <Person gate:gateId="1099" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1057;1081;1082;1083;1084;1085;1086;1087" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Barber</Person>&apos;s lawyer, <Person gate:gateId="1092" firstName="Paul" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Greene" kind="fullName">Paul Greene</Person>, added: &quot;Forensic toxicologists have looked at the case and understood... that it was impossible to have taken this amount of cocaine intentionally. &quot;You have inadvertent ingestion of cocaine that is passed to an athlete by way of kissing, which is exactly what happened.&quot; Although <Person gate:gateId="1100" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1057;1081;1082;1083;1084;1085;1086;1087" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Barber</Person>’s name has been cleared, he will have to forfeit his Canadian title and Championship record which he set on July 9 during the nation’s Olympic trials. Athletics <Location gate:gateId="1093" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1060;1065">Canada</Location> remarked: &quot;We are thankful that the proper procedures recognised the presence of a prohibited substance, but also in ensuring due process to the athlete in coming to a fair and reasonable decision.”