<Location gate:gateId="2011" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="1932;1942">MOSCOW</Location> — <Person gate:gateId="2012" firstName="Vladimir" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" initials="V." surname="Putin" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="1933;1938;1944;1946;1948;1962;2006;2007">Vladimir V. Putin</Person>, <Location gate:gateId="2013" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1934;1947;1949;1952;1955;1958">Russia</Location>’s president, hardly misses a chance to talk tough on terrorism, once famously saying he would find Chechen terrorists sitting in the “outhouse” and “rub them out.” He and <Person gate:gateId="2014" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Trump" kind="personName" rule="PersonTitleGenderUnknown" title="President" gate:matches="1935;1936;1939;1961">President Trump</Person>, notably dismissive of political correctness, would seem to have found common language on fighting terrorism — except on one point of, well, language. During his campaign, <Person gate:gateId="2015" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Trump" kind="personName" rule="PersonTitle" title="Mr." gate:matches="1935;1936;1939;1961">Mr. Trump</Person> associated Islam with terrorism and criticized <Person gate:gateId="2016" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="unknown" surname="Obama" kind="personName" rule="PersonTitleGenderUnknown" title="President" gate:matches="1937;1940">President Obama</Person> for declining to use the phrase “radical Islamic terrorism.” However, <Person gate:gateId="2017" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" surname="Putin" kind="personName" rule="PersonTitle" title="Mr." gate:matches="1933;1938;1944;1946;1948;1962;2006;2007">Mr. Putin</Person>, whom <Person gate:gateId="2018" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Trump" kind="personName" rule="PersonTitle" title="Mr." gate:matches="1935;1936;1939;1961">Mr. Trump</Person> so openly admires for his toughness, has, for more than a decade, done exactly what <Person gate:gateId="2019" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="unknown" surname="Obama" kind="personName" rule="PersonTitleGenderUnknown" title="President" gate:matches="1937;1940">President Obama</Person> did. He has never described terrorists as “Islamic” and has repeatedly gone out of his way to denounce such language. “I would prefer Islam not be mentioned in vain alongside terrorism,” he said at a news conference in December, answering a question about the Islamic State, a group he often refers to as “the so-called Islamic State,” to emphasize a distinction with the Islamic religion. At the opening of a mosque in <Location gate:gateId="2022" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="1932;1942" kind="locName">Moscow</Location> in 2015, <Person gate:gateId="2024" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" surname="Putin" kind="personName" rule="PersonTitle" title="Mr." gate:matches="1933;1938;1944;1946;1948;1962;2006;2007">Mr. Putin</Person> spoke of terrorists who “cynically exploit religious feelings for political aims.” In the <Location gate:gateId="2026" locType="region" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Middle East</Location>, <Person gate:gateId="2028" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" surname="Putin" kind="personName" rule="PersonTitle" title="Mr." gate:matches="1933;1938;1944;1946;1948;1962;2006;2007">Mr. Putin</Person> said at the mosque opening, “terrorists from the so-called Islamic State are compromising a great world religion, compromising Islam, sowing hatred, killing people, including clergy,” and added that “their ideology is built on lies and blatant distortions of Islam.” He was careful to add, “<Location gate:gateId="2025" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="2005;2008;2009;2010" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Muslim</Location> leaders are bravely and fearlessly using their own influence to resist this extremist propaganda.” And, this being <Location gate:gateId="2030" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1934;1947;1949;1952;1955;1958">Russia</Location>, the failure to adhere to this Kremlin-determined interpretation is a prosecutable offense: The Russian news media are required by law to note in any mention of the Islamic State that the reference is to a banned terrorist organization of that name, lest it be misconstrued as denigrating religion. <Person gate:gateId="2031" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" surname="Putin" kind="personName" rule="PersonTitle" title="Mr." gate:matches="1933;1938;1944;1946;1948;1962;2006;2007">Mr. Putin</Person> does not take this stance to soothe the feelings of Western liberals, a group he dismisses as hypocritical in any case. “<Person gate:gateId="2021" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1933;1938;1944;1946;1948;1962;2006;2007" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Putin</Person> prides himself on <Location gate:gateId="2032" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1934;1947;1949;1952;1955;1958">Russia</Location>’s intelligence capabilities,” the Brookings Institution wrote in a study of the early formation of his counterterrorism policies. “Russian leaders think they know their enemy,” and it is not the governments of majority <Location gate:gateId="2027" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="2005;2008;2009;2010" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Muslim</Location> countries such as <Location gate:gateId="2033" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Iraq</Location> and <Location gate:gateId="2034" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Iran</Location>, or the majority of Muslims living in <Location gate:gateId="2035" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1934;1947;1949;1952;1955;1958" kind="locName">Russia</Location>. Instead, Russian counterterrorism strategy focused on financing and militarily backing moderate <Location gate:gateId="2029" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="2005;2008;2009;2010" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Muslim</Location> leaders, with the breakthrough in the Chechen war coming when the region’s imam, Akhmad Kadyrov, allied with the Russian military. His son, Ramzan Kadyrov, leads the region today. While embracing Islamic leaders as a centerpiece of its counterterrorism strategy, however, the Kremlin did not avoid drawing distinctions along religious lines. The Russian government backed the Kadyrov family’s campaign to revive traditional Sufi Islam in <Location gate:gateId="2036" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1954;1956" kind="locName">Chechnya</Location> as a counterweight to the more austere Wahhabi denomination professed by many separatists. The Wahhabi strain was outlawed in another restive, predominantly <Location gate:gateId="2020" locType="unknown" rule="UnknownLocKey" gate:matches="2005;2008;2009;2010">Muslim</Location> province, Dagestan, and its adherents are persecuted in <Location gate:gateId="2037" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1934;1947;1949;1952;1955;1958" kind="locName">Russia</Location>, rights groups say. Still, the alliance with moderate Islamic religious leaders became important in pacifying <Location gate:gateId="2038" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1954;1956">Chechnya</Location> and other <Location gate:gateId="2039" rule="LocKey" kind="locName" ruleFinal="LocFinal">North Caucasus</Location> regions, which have ceased to pose a serious security threat to <Location gate:gateId="2040" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1934;1947;1949;1952;1955;1958">Russia</Location>. “<Person gate:gateId="2023" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1933;1938;1944;1946;1948;1962;2006;2007" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Putin</Person> rules a multiconfessional country,” Orkhan Dzhemal, a commentator on Islamic affairs, said in a telephone interview, noting that in the <Location gate:gateId="2041" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">United States</Location>, in contrast, Muslims are not a powerful political force. “He cannot say ‘Islamic terrorism’ for a simple reason. He doesn’t want to alienate millions of Russians.” The term preferred in Russian political parlance is “international terrorism.” In a phone call on Friday, <Person gate:gateId="2042" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Trump" kind="personName" rule="PersonTitleGenderUnknown" title="President" gate:matches="1935;1936;1939;1961">President Trump</Person> and <Person gate:gateId="2043" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" surname="Putin" kind="personName" rule="PersonTitle" title="Mr." gate:matches="1933;1938;1944;1946;1948;1962;2006;2007">Mr. Putin</Person> discussed “real cooperation” in fighting terrorist groups in <Location gate:gateId="2044" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" kind="locName">Syria</Location>. They could agree on an enemy. But the Kremlin statement described a “priority placed on uniting forces in the fight against the main threat — international terrorism.”