A new scheme that hopes to encourage refugees from <Location gate:gateId="1076" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1042;1057">Syria</Location> and other nations to start new lives in <Location gate:gateId="1077" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="region" gate:matches="1043;1052" kind="locName">Asia</Location> and <Location gate:gateId="1078" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1044;1053">Latin America</Location> is to be funded by the British government, <Person gate:gateId="1079" firstName="Theresa" rule="GazPerson" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" surname="May" kind="fullName">Theresa May</Person> has said. The commitment, part of a package of measures to help alleviate the crisis of migrants and refugees seeking to reach <Location gate:gateId="1080" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="region" gate:matches="1046;1050">Europe</Location> via the <Location gate:gateId="1081" locType="region" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Mediterranean</Location>, forms part of £30m in funding announced by Downing Street at an <Organization gate:gateId="1082" orgType="other" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">EU</Organization> summit in <Location gate:gateId="1083" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" kind="locName">Malta</Location>. Among measures intended to reduce the flow of people seeking to reach <Location gate:gateId="1084" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="region" gate:matches="1046;1050">Europe</Location> is £2.5m in <Location gate:gateId="1085" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1051;1056;1062" kind="locName">UK</Location> funding for a UN-organised scheme intended to see richer nations help countries in <Location gate:gateId="1086" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="region" gate:matches="1043;1052" kind="locName">Asia</Location> and <Location gate:gateId="1087" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1044;1053">Latin America</Location> accept and support some refugees. The spending will include supplies for thousands of refugees facing desperate conditions in <Location gate:gateId="1088" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" kind="locName">Greece</Location> and <Location gate:gateId="1089" locType="pre" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">eastern Europe</Location>, including warm clothes, shelter and medical care. There is also a special <Location gate:gateId="1070" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1051;1056;1062">UK</Location> fund to support vulnerable female refugees travelling alone. The voluntary programme, officially called the emerging resettlement countries joint support mechanism, is at an early stage – none of the host countries has yet been confirmed – but is intended to help both the refugees and the countries they arrive in. It would see countries get help building factories or other infrastructure for the new arrivals, who would provide manual labour and in some cases skills, such as those of engineers or doctors, many of whom have fled <Location gate:gateId="1071" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1042;1057">Syria</Location>. Jointly run by the <Organization gate:gateId="1072" orgType="other" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1058;1059">UN</Organization> refugee agency and the International Organisation for Migration, the scheme is intended to help up to 30,000 people move over three years. The total cost is expected to be about £90m. It was first announced as part of a <Organization gate:gateId="1073" orgType="other" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1058;1059">UN</Organization> summit on refugees held in September. The international development secretary, Priti Patel, whose department jointly made the announcement, said <Location gate:gateId="1074" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Britain</Location> was “stepping up its support for the most vulnerable refugees who are at risk and need our help”. “This latest support from the <Location gate:gateId="1075" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1051;1056;1062">UK</Location> will help those who decide they want to return home to do so safely, protect men, women and children from exploitation, and ensure that those caught in freezing conditions get the basic help they need to survive,” she said.