<Person gate:gateId="838" firstName="Cristiano" rule="UnknownSurname" gender="male" gate:matches="826;802;804;806;811;813" surname="Ronaldo" kind="personName">Cristiano Ronaldo</Person> has stepped in to help 80 dogs housed in a shelter facing financial difficulties, according to reports in his home country of <Location gate:gateId="840" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="798;805">Portugal</Location>. The Real <Location gate:gateId="841" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Madrid</Location> forward, who turned 32 last week, has often been praised for his charity work, topping a list of the world’s most generous athletes in 2015. <Person gate:gateId="828" firstName="Ronaldo" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="826;802;804;806;811;813">Ronaldo</Person>’s latest act of kindness came in response to a request from Cantinho <Person gate:gateId="839" firstName="da" rule="UnknownSurname" surname="Lili" kind="personName">da Lili</Person>, a dog rescue centre based in Gouveia which has struggled to meet veterinary bills of up to €2,000. After a volunteer at the centre contacted a friend of <Person gate:gateId="829" firstName="Ronaldo" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="826;802;804;806;811;813">Ronaldo</Person>’s family, the <Location gate:gateId="830" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="798;805">Portugal</Location> international sent an autographed shirt to the centre, which will now be auctioned off to raise vital funds. “I want to thank <Person gate:gateId="831" rule="FirstPersonStop" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" gate:matches="826;802;804;806;811;813" kind="firstName">Ronaldo</Person> from the bottom of my heart. It&apos;s a simple gesture, but very important,” <Person gate:gateId="832" firstName="Liliana" rule="PersonLocAmbig" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" surname="Santos" kind="fullName">Liliana Santos</Person>, one of workers at the dog shelter, told Correrio de Mahna. The shirt was sent to the shelter last November but was only received this week due to difficulties with the delivery. “The important thing is that it&apos;s already here and we still do not believe it,&quot; said <Person gate:gateId="833" firstName="Gloria" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" surname="Carvalho" kind="fullName">Gloria Carvalho</Person>, the volunteer who initiated the contact with <Person gate:gateId="834" firstName="Ronaldo" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="826;802;804;806;811;813">Ronaldo</Person>’s family. At the tail end of last year, <Person gate:gateId="835" firstName="Ronaldo" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="826;802;804;806;811;813">Ronaldo</Person> sent a video message via his Instagram account to the children of <Location gate:gateId="836" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Syria</Location> affected by the county’s long-running civil war, telling them they are “true heroes”. The former <Location gate:gateId="837" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Manchester</Location> United forward also made a “generous donation” to Save the Children, the international non-governmental organisation, for whom he works as an ambassador.