In all that is being said about <Person gate:gateId="2652" firstName="Theresa" rule="GazPerson" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" surname="May" kind="fullName">Theresa May</Person>, Brexit and her relations with <Person gate:gateId="2653" firstName="Donald" rule="GazPerson" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Trump" kind="fullName">Donald Trump</Person>, little attention has been given to the extraordinary workload of the Prime Minister. At the end of last month, May spent Thursday and Friday in <Location gate:gateId="2654" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" kind="locName">Washington</Location> to meet the new <Location gate:gateId="2655" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">US</Location> President. She then flew to <Location gate:gateId="2656" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Turkey</Location> on Saturday. On Monday she went to <Location gate:gateId="2657" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Cardiff</Location> to meet the leaders of the devolved administrations who each have concerns about Brexit, and on Tuesday she travelled to <Location gate:gateId="2658" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Dublin</Location> to meet the leadership of the <Organization gate:gateId="2659" orgType="other" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2582;2588;2613">EU</Organization> member state with most reason to be concerned about the <Location gate:gateId="2660" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="2583;2602">UK</Location>’s intended departure. On Wednesday she was back in the <Organization gate:gateId="2661" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">House of Commons</Organization> for her weekly session of Prime Minister’s Questions. But by Friday was on the move again, heading to <Location gate:gateId="2662" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Malta</Location> for the informal meeting with <Organization gate:gateId="2663" orgType="other" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2582;2588;2613">EU</Organization> leaders. The Prime Minister must play her best possible game at a series of highly-charged European summits and council meetings. There will inevitably be one key theme of the main international forums including the <Organization gate:gateId="2664" orgType="other" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">G8</Organization> and G20, and even the <Organization gate:gateId="2665" orgType="other" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Nato</Organization> summit and the Commonwealth Heads of <Organization gate:gateId="2666" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2591;2600">Government</Organization> Meeting: everyone wants to talk to her about Brexit. But how is the Prime Minister to cope with Brexit while running the country with a small majority? What about her domestic policies? She needs support. May cannot and should not delegate responsibility for Brexit to her ministerial colleagues. It is the issue that will define her premiership and she must be seen to take personal responsibility for it. The same argument applies to the wider diplomatic agenda which is so dominated by Brexit. Equally, she needs to keep a tight <Person gate:gateId="2667" rule="FirstPersonStop" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" kind="firstName">rein</Person> on her three cabinet colleagues with responsibility for Brexit: <Person gate:gateId="2668" firstName="Boris" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Johnson" kind="fullName">Boris Johnson</Person>, <Person gate:gateId="2669" firstName="David" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Davis" kind="fullName">David Davis</Person> and <Person gate:gateId="2670" firstName="Liam" rule="GazPerson" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Fox" kind="fullName">Liam Fox</Person>. She cannot give any one of the three ascendancy over the other two. But where else can she look for help? <Person gate:gateId="2671" firstName="Philip" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Hammond" kind="fullName" rule="GazPerson" gate:matches="2597;2598">Philip Hammond</Person>, the Chancellor, is the ultimate safe pair of hands. Sometimes rather dry in tone, <Person gate:gateId="2672" firstName="Hammond" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="2597;2598">Hammond</Person> is of one mind with the Prime Minister on matters economic. She need not worry that he needs watching, but he does not need the distraction of a second job overseeing his cabinet colleagues. The potential so far unseen hazards for May’s <Organization gate:gateId="2673" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2591;2600">Government</Organization> are not so much on the foreign or economic desks but on the home front. The strain on the <Organization gate:gateId="2674" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">NHS</Organization>, the crisis in social care, the housing shortage, continuing chaos on the railways, discontent in the prisons. Any one of these – let alone two or three in combination – could provoke a serious political crisis. The <Location gate:gateId="2675" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="2583;2602">UK</Location>’s second female PM should perhaps remind herself that <Person gate:gateId="2676" firstName="Margaret" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" surname="Thatcher" kind="fullName" rule="GazPerson" gate:matches="2603;2624">Margaret Thatcher</Person> – who saw off <Person gate:gateId="2677" rule="PersonTitleGenderUnknown" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" title="General" gender="unknown" surname="Galtieri" kind="personName">General Galtieri</Person> and the <Organization gate:gateId="2678" orgType="unknown" rule="TheOrgXBase" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">National Union of Mineworkers</Organization> – was brought down by the seemingly dull issue of local government finance. May has also pledged to preserve the <Location gate:gateId="2679" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="2607;2611;2612">United Kingdom</Location>. It used to be said of <Person gate:gateId="2680" firstName="David" rule="GazPerson" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Cameron" kind="fullName">David Cameron</Person> that if he lost the referendum on independence for <Location gate:gateId="2681" locType="province" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Scotland</Location> he would be remembered for nothing else. He will now be remembered for his failure in a different referendum. The vacant title of The Prime Minister Who Broke The Union is May’s for the taking. To avoid such ignominies, the Prime Minister should appoint a senior minister who should handle relations with the nations and the regions of the <Location gate:gateId="2682" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="2607;2611;2612">United Kingdom</Location>; to look for compromises and ways to cement the <Location gate:gateId="2683" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="2607;2611;2612">United Kingdom</Location> together, while she detaches the country from the <Organization gate:gateId="2684" orgType="other" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2582;2588;2613">European Union</Organization>. The Prime Minister simply does not have the time to do all the jobs currently on her plate. Working with the devolved administrations, overseeing domestic policy, chairing <Organization gate:gateId="2685" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2614;2615">Cabinet</Organization> committees and knocking ministerial heads together, is a job for a deputy prime minister. Looking around her <Organization gate:gateId="2686" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2614;2615">Cabinet</Organization> table, few of May’s colleagues meet the dual criteria for the role of deputy: the authority to do the job but without appearing to be an alternative PM should the challenge of Brexit prove too great for May herself. <Person gate:gateId="2687" firstName="Michael" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Fallon" kind="fullName">Michael Fallon</Person>, the Defence Secretary, and <Person gate:gateId="2688" firstName="Damian" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Green" kind="fullName">Damian Green</Person>, Work and Pensions Secretary, are perhaps best qualified on grounds of loyalty and gravitas. <Person gate:gateId="2689" firstName="Amber" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" surname="Rudd" kind="fullName">Amber Rudd</Person>, the Home Secretary, and the Chancellor too obviously possible successors to the top and each is already holding down a big job. The role of DPM should not be combined with running a major department. An able and loyal deputy who enjoys the Prime Minister’s full backing should be an asset to May. And just in case anyone is tempted to suggest that appointing one might be interpreted as a sign of weakness, it is worth noting that <Location gate:gateId="2690" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Churchill</Location>, Attlee and <Person gate:gateId="2691" rule="GazPersonFirst" firstName="Blair" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" kind="firstName">Blair</Person> each had a Deputy PM throughout their time at Number 10 – as did <Person gate:gateId="2647" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" matchedWithLonger="true" surname="Thatcher" kind="personName" rule="PersonTitle" title="Mrs" gate:matches="2603;2624">Mrs Thatcher</Person> during her more successful first two terms. And on a more cautionary note, <Person gate:gateId="2648" firstName="Anthony" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Eden" kind="fullName">Anthony Eden</Person>, <Person gate:gateId="2649" firstName="Alec" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Douglas-Home" kind="fullName">Alec Douglas-Home</Person>, <Person gate:gateId="2650" firstName="Jim" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Callaghan" kind="fullName">Jim Callaghan</Person> and <Person gate:gateId="2651" firstName="Gordon" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Brown" kind="fullName">Gordon Brown</Person> were happy to do without.