<Location gate:gateId="809" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="776;777;782;787;789">UGANDA</Location> PLANS TO EXPORT ROASTED COFFEE TO EUROPE
  <Location gate:gateId="810" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="776;777;782;787;789">Uganda</Location> plans to export roasted coffee to
  <Location gate:gateId="811" locType="region" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Europe</Location> by the end of 1988, a prominent local businessman said.
      A.<Person gate:gateId="812" rule="PersonFullInitials" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gate:matches="780;802" initials="R." surname="Sendi" kind="fullName">R. Sendi</Person> said on Sunday that <Location gate:gateId="813" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="776;777;782;787;789">Uganda</Location>&apos;s Ministry of
  Industry supports his plan to build a factory to roast, grind
  and pack local coffee for export. Construction will start in
  December and the factory should be ready by next October.
      He said the <Organization gate:gateId="803" orgType="unknown" rule="TheOrgXBase" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Marketing Ministry</Organization> has authorised the Coffee
  Marketing Board to supply his company &amp;lt;Unipack&gt; with 24,000
  tonnes of beans a year for processing and export. <Person gate:gateId="804" rule="Unknown" matchedWithLonger="true" gate:matches="780;802" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Sendi</Person> also
  told reporters he had negotiated a 69.7 mln French franc loan
  from the Banque Industrielle d&apos;Afrique Oriental in <Location gate:gateId="805" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" kind="locName">Paris</Location>.
      <Location gate:gateId="806" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="776;777;782;787;789">Uganda</Location> is the world&apos;s fifth largest coffee producer, and
  expects to produce about 200,000 tonnes this year.
      Market sources say roasted coffee exports will benefit
  <Location gate:gateId="807" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="776;777;782;787;789">Uganda</Location>&apos;s economy as they will not be included in the 2.38 mln
  (60 kg) bag export quota assigned to the country under the
  latest International Coffee Agreement.
      In addition, the value of roasted coffee should be
  substantially higher than that of unroasted beans, they said.
      The <Location gate:gateId="808" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">U.S.</Location> Is the biggest buyer of Ugandan coffee, most of
  which is used to produce instant coffee.
  

