SMUGGLING BLAMED FOR CLOSURE OF <Organization gate:gateId="1372" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1329;1361" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">HAITIAN</Organization> SUGAR FIRM
  A sugar mill which was this
  nation&apos;s second largest employer closed its doors yesterday,
  saying it had been run out of business by sugar smuggled from
  <Location gate:gateId="1368" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Miami</Location> and the neighbouring <Location gate:gateId="1370" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Dominican Republic</Location>.
      The closure of the <Organization gate:gateId="1371" orgType="unknown" rule="OrgXEnding" ruleFinal="OrgCountryFinal" gate:matches="1329;1361">Haitian American Sugar Company</Organization> (HASCO)
  will idle 3,500 employees and affect as many as 30,000 to
  40,000 small sugar cane planters in regions around the capital,
  the company said.
      &quot;Because of unprecedented and ever-growing smuggling, HASCO
  regrets ... It cannot continue to accept delivery of sugar cane
  after April 10,&quot; the mill warned planters earlier this week.
      Since <Person gate:gateId="1375" firstName="Jean-Claude" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="unknown" surname="Duvalier" kind="personName" rule="PersonTitleGenderUnknown" title="President" gate:matches="1332;1363;1364">President Jean-Claude Duvalier</Person> fled <Location gate:gateId="1377" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Haiti</Location> fourteen
  months ago, widescale smuggling of basic goods such as cooking
  oil, flour, rice, sugar and canned milk has lowered consumer
  prices but bankrupted several local manufacturers, throwing
  hundreds of thousands of Haitians out of work.
      At the HASCO compound, where grim-faced workers lined up to
  receive their last pay, Spokesman <Person gate:gateId="1378" firstName="Georges" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" initials="D." surname="Rigaud" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="1334;1357;1358;1359;1362">Georges D. Rigaud</Person> showed a
  warehouse stocked with an estimated 445,000 unsold 100-pound
  (45-kg) bags of sugar.
      &quot;We are closing because of our huge stock of unsold sugar.
  We have no money left to continue operations,&quot; <Person gate:gateId="1365" rule="PersonSays" matchedWithLonger="true" gender="male" gate:matches="1334;1357;1358;1359;1362">Rigaud</Person> said.
      He said the company owed 7.6 mln dlrs and had borrowed an
  additional 1.5 mln dlrs in order to pay off workers.
      <Person gate:gateId="1373" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1334;1357;1358;1359;1362" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Rigaud</Person> blamed the mill&apos;s problems on an order by <Person gate:gateId="1374" rule="Unknown" matchedWithLonger="true" gate:matches="1332;1363;1364" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Duvalier</Person>
  two years ago forbidding HASCO from refining sugar.
      He said the government then began importing refined sugar
  at world market prices and reselling it at a huge profit and
  the provisional military-civilian government that replaced
  <Person gate:gateId="1376" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1332;1363;1364" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Duvalier</Person> last year continued the policy.
      &quot;But now with all the smuggling even the state can&apos;t compete
  with smuggled Dominican refined sugar,&quot; <Person gate:gateId="1366" rule="PersonSays" matchedWithLonger="true" gender="male" gate:matches="1334;1357;1358;1359;1362">Rigaud</Person> said.
      HASCO workers earned 4.20 dlrs daily, considerably above
  the usual minimum wage of three dlrs.
      It is generally estimated that every employed Haitian
  supports at least six people. <Person gate:gateId="1367" rule="PersonSays" matchedWithLonger="true" gender="male" gate:matches="1334;1357;1358;1359;1362">Rigaud</Person> said HASCO&apos;s closing at a
  minimum would affect 280,000 to 300,000 people.
      Laid-off workers were bitter about the closure. &quot;We&apos;re dead,
  and it&apos;s the government that&apos;s causing us to die,&quot; declared
  <Person gate:gateId="1369" firstName="Lucien" rule="UnknownSurname" surname="Felix" kind="personName">Lucien Felix</Person>, 34, who has five dependents.
  

