RPT - <Organization gate:gateId="1778" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1737;1738;1759" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">EUROPEAN</Organization> TRADE MAY PROPOSE NEW ICO FORMULA
  European coffee traders and roasters
  may propose a new formula for calculating International Coffee
  Organization (<Person gate:gateId="1775" rule="GazPersonFirst" firstName="ICO" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" gate:matches="1723;1727;1731;1747" kind="firstName">ICO</Person>) coffee quotas at the end of their meeting
  here this week, traders and officials told <Organization gate:gateId="1776" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Reuters</Organization>.
      Although traders were unwilling to reveal details of the
  possible new formula, they said it would give <Location gate:gateId="1777" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1726;1729;1743;1746">Brazil</Location>, the
  world&apos;s biggest coffee producer, unchanged <Person gate:gateId="1779" rule="GazPersonFirst" firstName="ICO" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" gate:matches="1723;1727;1731;1747" kind="firstName">ICO</Person> quotas for the
  next two years and could be a basis for renegotiation.
      &quot;The main sticking point on quotas has been <Location gate:gateId="1760" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1726;1729;1743;1746">Brazil</Location>&apos;s
  attitude, and this compromise could be a solution, &quot; one said.
      However, the European coffee trade federation meeting,
  which began here today and is to continue to the end of the
  week, has revealed gaps in the European position on
  re-introducing quotas.
      Traders said that, as a whole, the trade side was against
  re-introduction of <Person gate:gateId="1761" rule="GazPersonFirst" firstName="ICO" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" gate:matches="1723;1727;1731;1747" kind="firstName">ICO</Person> quotas, while roasters were generally in
  favour with the single proviso that there had to be some
  formula basis for re-allocating quota shares among producing
  countries.
      The roasters said the positions were generally fairly
  close, and problems with some <Organization gate:gateId="1762" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1732;1735">Government</Organization> officials.
      <Location gate:gateId="1763" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1733;1736">Germany</Location> and <Location gate:gateId="1764" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Italy</Location> were cited as the extremes of polarized
  <Organization gate:gateId="1765" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1732;1735">Government</Organization> attitudes, with most other countries on the fence.
      Sources said <Location gate:gateId="1766" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1733;1736">Germany</Location> was the most extreme against quota
  re-introduction, while the Italians were most in favour.
      &quot;Nevertheless, we expect to find enough common ground by the
  end of the week to at least present a common <Organization gate:gateId="1767" orgType="other" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1737;1738;1759">European Community</Organization>
  (<Organization gate:gateId="1768" orgType="other" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1737;1738;1759">EC</Organization>) view at the next meeting of consumer members of the
  International Coffee Agreement (ICA) in July,&quot; one trader said.
      &quot;We hope we can present the compromise proposal and that not
  only the consumer side, but the producer side will accept it,&quot;
  one official said.
      &quot;We have learned that we can live without the quotas that
  were suspended in February last year, but would prefer the
  stability they can bring to the market as long as we do not
  simply return to the old and outdated status quo as far as
  quota allocation is concerned,&quot; he added.
      Overall, however, trader and roaster opinion on the
  likelihood of a successful re-negotiation was mildly
  pessimistic, varying between a 50-50 chance and 60-40 against.
      &quot;Our main difficulty will be to persuade the <Location gate:gateId="1769" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1742;1744">U.S.</Location> On the
  consumer side and <Location gate:gateId="1770" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1726;1729;1743;1746">Brazil</Location> on the producer side to agree to quota
  re-introduction, &quot; he said.
      &quot;The <Location gate:gateId="1771" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1742;1744">U.S.</Location> Position has, if anything, hardened, while the new
  <Organization gate:gateId="1772" orgType="unknown" rule="OrgXBase" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Brazilian Coffee Institute</Organization> president has adopted the least
  negotiable position of any of his predecessors,&quot; one trader
  said.
      &quot;However, with many producers starting to swing in favour of
  the consumer position that quotas have to be re-allocated under
  a new formula, <Location gate:gateId="1773" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1726;1729;1743;1746">Brazil</Location> is becoming increasingly isolated, which
  gives at least some hope of a compromise at the <Person gate:gateId="1774" rule="GazPersonFirst" firstName="ICO" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" gate:matches="1723;1727;1731;1747" kind="firstName">ICO</Person> quota
  meeting in September,&quot; the official said.
  

