Independent booksellers are being sent reinforcements in the battle against <Location gate:gateId="2391" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="region" gate:matches="2297;2310;2314;2315;2316">Amazon</Location> with a website that will support the dwindling band of high street traders, backed by the world&apos;s largest publisher. My Independent Bookshop, a social network for book lovers from Penguin Random <Organization gate:gateId="2392" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2298;2300;2308;2313">House</Organization>, launches on Thursday as an online space where anyone can review their favourite books and show off their good taste on virtual shelves. Crucially, readers can also buy books from the site, with a small proportion of takings going to support scores of local independent book stores. Around 70 shops are connected to the site so far and Penguin Random <Organization gate:gateId="2395" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2298;2300;2308;2313">House</Organization> hopes several hundred will eventually sign up. A reader&apos;s nominated home store – which doesn&apos;t have to be geographically close – will get 5% of the revenues from every physical book they buy and 8% on an ebook. The site is a tie-up with the e-commerce website Hive, which has been offering a similar service to local shops since 2011. <Person gate:gateId="2397" firstName="Terry" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Pratchett" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="2302;2362;2363;2364">Terry Pratchett</Person> described My Independent Bookshop as &quot;a very, very good thing&quot;, and other authors such as <Person gate:gateId="2398" firstName="Lisa" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" surname="Jewell" kind="fullName">Lisa Jewell</Person>, <Person gate:gateId="2365" firstName="Alastair" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Campbell" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="2304;2326">Alastair Campbell</Person>, <Person gate:gateId="2366" firstName="Irvine" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Welsh" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="2305;2321">Irvine Welsh</Person> and <Person gate:gateId="2367" firstName="Tony" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Parsons" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="2306;2320">Tony Parsons</Person> have registered on the site during a month-long testing phase. <Person gate:gateId="2368" firstName="Dan" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Franklin" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="2307;2309;2312">Dan Franklin</Person>, digital publisher at Penguin Random <Organization gate:gateId="2369" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2298;2300;2308;2313">House</Organization>, said national chains, such as Waterstones or Foyles, had not been included in an attempt to recreate the independence and quirkiness of non-chain bookshops. <Person gate:gateId="2370" firstName="Franklin" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="2307;2309;2312">Franklin</Person> said the publishing giant would not make money from the website, but saw other benefits. &quot;The data is very valuable. We can see what&apos;s trending, what books are popular and how people are interacting.&quot; He described the site as &quot;a way of having a more direct conversation with consumers&quot;, who will have the chance to compete for prizes from rare proof copies to attending author events. The venture underscores how publishers are seeking a closer relationship with readers, as the book world goes through its biggest upheaval since the invention of high-speed printing presses and the railways. Publishers find they are competing with an ever increasing array of entertainment choices on smartphones and mobile devices, while high street bookshops have been closing their doors in the face of cut-throat competition from <Location gate:gateId="2371" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="region" gate:matches="2297;2310;2314;2315;2316">Amazon</Location> and supermarkets. Recent data revealing that fewer than 1,000 independent bookshops remain in the <Location gate:gateId="2372" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">UK</Location> raised alarm bells about the future of the industry. <Person gate:gateId="2373" firstName="Franklin" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="2307;2309;2312">Franklin</Person> said the Penguin Random <Organization gate:gateId="2374" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2298;2300;2308;2313">House</Organization> venture was not intended to rival <Location gate:gateId="2375" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="region" gate:matches="2297;2310;2314;2315;2316">Amazon</Location>. &quot;<Location gate:gateId="2376" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="region" gate:matches="2297;2310;2314;2315;2316">Amazon</Location> is a partner of ours and it is in our interest to support what they do.&quot; The publisher has decided against using &quot;intrusive&quot; algorithms – favoured by <Location gate:gateId="2377" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="region" gate:matches="2297;2310;2314;2315;2316">Amazon</Location> - to suggest books readers might like. Instead recommendations will come from the site&apos;s users with the aim of creating a &quot;serendipitous way of discovering books&quot;. The publisher is staying tight-lipped about the target number of users for this &quot;desert island discs for books&quot; – but is hoping large numbers of book lovers will sign up, as well as organisations. The site&apos;s creators are also counting on readers&apos; natural curiosity to peer onto other people&apos;s book shelves. Several readers and authors have already created a personal page – &quot;a bookshop&quot; – showcasing 12 books they like. <Person gate:gateId="2393" rule="Unknown" matchedWithLonger="true" gender="male" gate:matches="2302;2362;2363;2364" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Pratchett</Person> has chosen books by fellow sci-fi hit authors <Person gate:gateId="2378" firstName="Douglas" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Adams" kind="fullName">Douglas Adams</Person> and <Person gate:gateId="2379" firstName="Neil" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Gaiman" kind="fullName">Neil Gaiman</Person>, but also praises Lynne Truss&apos;s punctuation book Eats, <Organization gate:gateId="2380" orgType="unknown" rule="OrgXandY" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Shoots &amp; Leaves</Organization> – &quot;I come back to this over and over again,&quot; he writes on the site. <Person gate:gateId="2381" firstName="Tony" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Parsons" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="2306;2320">Tony Parsons</Person>&apos;s page is themed around crime novels and thrillers, while the author of Trainspotting, <Person gate:gateId="2382" firstName="Irvine" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Welsh" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="2305;2321">Irvine Welsh</Person>, has created a list that includes <Person gate:gateId="2383" firstName="Fyodor" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Dostoyevsky" kind="fullName">Fyodor Dostoyevsky</Person>&apos;s The Brothers Karamazov and <Person gate:gateId="2384" firstName="George" rule="PersonLocAmbig" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Orwell" kind="fullName">George Orwell</Person>&apos;s Keep the Aspidistra Flying – &quot;a completely harrowing and stark account of poverty&quot;, he writes of the grim story of a downtrodden would-be poet in 1930s <Location gate:gateId="2385" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">London</Location>. <Person gate:gateId="2386" firstName="Alastair" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Campbell" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="2304;2326">Alastair Campbell</Person> has not yet revealed the contents of his shelf, although the former New Labour spin doctor and author of several works of fiction and non-fiction has registered on the site. The venture could be a shot in the arm for independent stores, such as <Location gate:gateId="2387" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Hayling Island</Location> Bookshop in <Location gate:gateId="2388" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="region" kind="locName">Hampshire</Location>, selected by <Person gate:gateId="2394" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="2302;2362;2363;2364" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Pratchett</Person> as the shop to profit from his orders. <Person gate:gateId="2396" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="2302;2362;2363;2364" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Pratchett</Person> launched his novel Nation in the shop in 2008, but <Person gate:gateId="2389" firstName="Colin" rule="PersonLocAmbig" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Telford" kind="fullName">Colin Telford</Person>, the store&apos;s events manager, said staff were astonished when they heard the best-selling fantasy author had chosen them. He said it was too early to tell how far Hayling Island could gain but expects &quot;some additional income from people we wouldn&apos;t normally see&quot;. <Location gate:gateId="2390" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Telford</Location> said the decline in independent bookshops had probably reached its limits, as those booksellers remaining turn to events, cafes and social media to draw in shoppers. &quot;Those independent bookshops that are still going are probably going to survive because they have worked out their survival strategy.&quot;