<Location gate:gateId="859" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="831;833">INDIA</Location> RELAXES RULES FOR EXPORT PROMOTION
  The <Organization gate:gateId="851" orgType="unknown" rule="TheOrgXBase" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Reserve Bank of India</Organization>, <Person gate:gateId="853" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="847;848;849;850" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">RBI</Person>,
  announced new rules to allow exporters of 25 products to use
  foreign exchange up to 10 pct of their firm&apos;s total annual
  export earnings for export promotion abroad.
      The move is designed by the government to improve <Location gate:gateId="854" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="831;833">India</Location>&apos;s
  trade deficit.
      Products eligible for the new Blanket Exchange Permit
  Scheme include tea bags, cigarettes, coffee, leather, various
  textiles, chemicals, pharmaceuticals, plastics, engineering and
  electronic goods, ready-made garments, processed food, sports
  goods, fabricated <Person gate:gateId="855" rule="GazPersonFirst" firstName="mica" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" kind="firstName">mica</Person> and consultancy services.
      The scheme replaces current rules which allow different
  amounts of foreign exchange to be used only when firms attain a
  minimum annual turnover prescribed for each product.
      <Person gate:gateId="858" rule="PersonSays" gate:matches="847;848;849;850">RBI</Person> said under the new rule, 16 other products will
  qualify, on a discretionary basis, for overseas promotional
  spending of not more than two pct of the freight-on-board value
  of annual export earnings.
      These include oil cakes, cereals, raw cotton, raw and
  semi-processed leather, gems, <Person gate:gateId="857" rule="GazPersonFirst" firstName="castor" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" kind="firstName">castor</Person> and sandalwood oil,
  psyllium husks and seeds, opium and various mineral ores.
      <Person gate:gateId="852" rule="PersonSays" gate:matches="847;848;849;850">RBI</Person> said exporters of products not covered by either of the
  two groups will be eligible to use up to five pct of their
  freight-on-board value of their annual export earnings.
      Industry sources said the new entitlements, considerably
  higher than the previous limits, are also more flexible because
  holders of new permits no longer need to frequently apply to
  <Person gate:gateId="856" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="847;848;849;850" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">RBI</Person> for release of foreign exchange for export purposes.
  

