<Location gate:gateId="1012" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="province" gate:matches="966;974;975;978;981">Bayern</Location> <Location gate:gateId="1013" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Munich</Location> <Person gate:gateId="1017" rule="PersonTitle1" gate:matches="1006;1007;1009">captain Philipp Lahm</Person> does not believe he will be able to maintain his high standards next year after announcing he will retire from football at the end of the season. The 33-year-old has a year left on his contract with the defending Bundesliga champions but will walk away early - also saying he has rejected an offer from the club to become a sporting director. He admits he has been considering his future for some time and will give his all for the rest of the campaign. &quot;I&apos;m going to stop playing football at the end of the season,&quot; the <Person gate:gateId="1014" rule="PersonFullInitials" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gate:matches="970;973" initials="FC" surname="Bayern" kind="fullName">FC Bayern</Person> youth product confirmed on the club&apos;s official website following his team&apos;s 1-0 victory over VfL Wolfsburg in Tuesday evening&apos;s <Person gate:gateId="1015" rule="PersonFullInitials" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gate:matches="972;1008;1010;1011" initials="DFB" surname="Cup" kind="fullName">DFB Cup</Person> Round of 16 tie. &quot;More than a year ago I started checking and questioning myself from day to day and week to week. I&apos;m certain I&apos;ll maintain peak form through to the end of the season. I can manage that until the end of the campaign, but not beyond it.&quot; On the chance to join the club&apos;s backroom staff, he added: &quot;There were talks, and in the end I decided it&apos;s not the right time for me to take up a new position at <Person gate:gateId="1016" rule="PersonFullInitials" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gate:matches="970;973" initials="FC" surname="Bayern" kind="fullName">FC Bayern</Person>.&quot; <Person gate:gateId="1019" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1006;1007;1009" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Lahm</Person> announced the news after <Location gate:gateId="1018" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="province" gate:matches="966;974;975;978;981">Bayern</Location>&apos;s 1-0 win over Wolfsburg in the DFB-Pokal, having made his 500th <Location gate:gateId="1020" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="province" gate:matches="966;974;975;978;981">Bayern</Location> appearance against Schalke on Saturday. A World <Person gate:gateId="1021" rule="Unknown" matchedWithLonger="true" gate:matches="972;1008;1010;1011" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Cup</Person> winner with <Location gate:gateId="1023" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="977;982">Germany</Location>, <Person gate:gateId="1022" rule="Unknown" matchedWithLonger="true" gate:matches="1006;1007;1009" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Lahm</Person> is aiming to win a record eighth Bundesliga title this season. The Munich-born player has spent his entire club career with <Location gate:gateId="1025" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="province" gate:matches="966;974;975;978;981">Bayern</Location>, bar a two-year loan spell at <Location gate:gateId="1027" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Stuttgart</Location> between 2003 and 2005. He has won seven Bundesliga titles, six DFB-Pokals, the Champions League and the Club World <Person gate:gateId="1024" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="972;1008;1010;1011" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Cup</Person> with <Location gate:gateId="1028" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="province" gate:matches="966;974;975;978;981">Bayern</Location>. He captained <Location gate:gateId="1029" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="977;982">Germany</Location> to World <Person gate:gateId="1026" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="972;1008;1010;1011" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Cup</Person> glory in 2014 before announcing his retirement from international football.