<Organization gate:gateId="1497" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1446;1486" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">INDONESIAN</Organization> <Organization gate:gateId="1489" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">COMMODITY EXCHANGE</Organization> MAY EXPAND
  The <Organization gate:gateId="1490" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgCountryFinal" gate:matches="1446;1486">Indonesian Commodity Exchange</Organization> is
  likely to start trading in at least one new commodity, and
  possibly two, during calendar 1987, exchange chairman <Person gate:gateId="1492" rule="PersonSays" gate:matches="1482;1483;1485">Paian
  Nainggolan</Person> said.
      He told <Organization gate:gateId="1491" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Reuters</Organization> in a telephone interview that trading in
  palm oil, sawn timber, pepper or tobacco was being considered.
      Trading in either crude palm oil (CPO) or refined palm oil
  may also be introduced. But he said the question was still
  being considered by Trade <Person gate:gateId="1499" rule="Unknown" matchedWithLonger="true" gate:matches="1484;1487;1488" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Minister</Person> Rachmat <Person gate:gateId="1501" rule="Unknown" matchedWithLonger="true" gate:matches="1484;1487;1488" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Saleh</Person> and no
  decision on when to go ahead had been made.
      The fledgling exchange currently trades coffee and rubber
  physicals on an open outcry system four days a week.
      &quot;Several factors make us move cautiously,&quot; <Person gate:gateId="1493" matchedWithLonger="true" rule="PersonSays" gate:matches="1482;1483;1485">Nainggolan</Person> said.
  &quot;We want to move slowly and safely so that we do not make a
  mistake and undermine confidence in the exchange.&quot;
      Physical rubber trading was launched in 1985, with coffee
  added in January 1986. Rubber contracts are traded FOB, up to
  five months forward. Robusta coffee grades four and five are
  traded for prompt delivery and up to five months forward,
  exchange officials said.
      The trade ministry and exchange board are considering the
  introduction of futures trading later for rubber, but one
  official said a feasibility study was needed first. No
  decisions are likely until after <Location gate:gateId="1494" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1451;1454">Indonesia</Location>&apos;s elections on April
  23, traders said.
      Trade <Person gate:gateId="1495" rule="PersonSays" gate:matches="1484;1487;1488">Minister Saleh</Person> said on Monday that <Location gate:gateId="1498" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1451;1454">Indonesia</Location>, as the
  world&apos;s second largest producer of natural rubber, should
  expand its rubber marketing effort and he hoped development of
  the exchange would help this.
      <Person gate:gateId="1496" matchedWithLonger="true" rule="PersonSays" gate:matches="1482;1483;1485">Nainggolan</Person> said that the exchange was trying to boost
  overseas interest by building up contacts with end-users.
      He said teams had already been to <Location gate:gateId="1500" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">South Korea</Location> and <Location gate:gateId="1502" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Taiwan</Location> to
  encourage direct use of the exchange, while a delegation would
  also visit <Location gate:gateId="1503" locType="region" rule="GazLocation" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Europe</Location>, <Location gate:gateId="1504" locType="country" rule="GazLocation" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Mexico</Location> and some Latin American states to
  encourage participation.
      Officials say the infant exchange has made a good start
  although trading in coffee has been disappointing.
      Transactions in rubber between the start of trading in
  April 1985 and December 1986 totalled 9,595 tonnes, worth 6.9
  mln dlrs FOB, plus 184.3 mln rupiah for rubber delivered
  locally, the latest exchange report said.
       Trading in coffee in calendar 1986 amounted to only 1,905
  tonnes in 381 lots, valued at 6.87 billion rupiah.
       <Organization gate:gateId="1505" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Total</Organization> membership of the exchange is now nine brokers and
  44 traders.
  

