Usain Bolt insists he is fit and ready to race ahead of his first 200 metres of the season at the Muller Anniversary Games on Friday night. The six-time Olympic champion faces a key test of his fitness when he races for the first time since pulling out of the Jamaican trials with a hamstring strain. &quot;I&apos;m good, I&apos;m feeling good, been training good now, I&apos;m happy with where I am,&quot; the 29-year-old told a packed press conference. &quot;My hamstring is good, I have no issue right now. I know I&apos;m in good shape.&quot; Bolt&apos;s outing at the <Location gate:gateId="1655" rule="LocationPost" kind="locName" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Olympic Stadium</Location>, the scene of his three Olympic gold medal wins at <Location gate:gateId="1656" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="1614;1627">London</Location> 2012 in the 100m, 200m and sprint relay, will be his last before the <Person gate:gateId="1646" firstName="Rio" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Games" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="1616;1617;1624">Rio Games</Person>, where he will bid for an unprecedented &apos;triple triple&apos; of Olympic crowns. &quot;I&apos;ll definitely be there, I&apos;m excited to go,&quot; the Jamaican said of his <Person gate:gateId="1647" firstName="Rio" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="1616;1617;1624">Rio</Person> hopes. &quot;This is where history is going to be made, I&apos;m excited to put on a show for the entire world to see. &quot;This is my final Olympics, it&apos;s a big one.&quot; Bolt is familiar at dealing with, and defying, doubters, especially last year when he went into the World Championships in <Location gate:gateId="1648" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" kind="locName">Beijing</Location> trailing two-time convicted drug cheat <Person gate:gateId="1649" firstName="Justin" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Gatlin" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="1620;1645">Justin Gatlin</Person> in the 100m and 200m world rankings only to leave <Location gate:gateId="1650" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">China</Location> with the complete set of gold medals. &quot;I&apos;m definitely a tough competitor,&quot; he said. &quot;Last year <Person gate:gateId="1654" rule="Unknown" matchedWithLonger="true" gender="male" gate:matches="1620;1645" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Gatlin</Person> was just not ready, it was the first time he was being chased. &quot;It was hard for him, but this year is not going to be the same, I am in much better shape, so I won&apos;t leave it to the last second.&quot; Bolt insisted he was never worried his hamstring problem would rule him out of <Person gate:gateId="1651" firstName="Rio" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="1616;1617;1624">Rio</Person>. &quot;When I got to the doctor he said if I had competed (in the trials) I would probably would have torn my hamstring really badly,&quot; he said. &quot;I made the right decision. My coach always makes sure I put my health first. But I was never really worried because my coach always figures out a way to adjust the programme. &quot;I was in pretty good shape before I had to pull out, so I wasn&apos;t really worried.&quot; It is now seven years since Bolt clocked his 100m and 200m world records of 9.58 and 19.19 seconds respectively and, with his intention to retire after the 2017 World Championships in <Location gate:gateId="1652" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="1614;1627" kind="locName">London</Location>, the chances of him breaking them appear slim. Bolt, though, says he is focused on lowering his time in the 200m, an event he has always described as his favourite. &quot;I&apos;m happy that I didn&apos;t get a really bad setback this season, it was up and down, but I could always train,&quot; he added. &quot;I think the competition, the energy, the work they have to put in to win the 100m in <Location gate:gateId="1653" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" kind="locName">Rio</Location> will help my 200m and that&apos;s really my focus, trying to break the 200m world record.&quot;