Finance Minister <Person gate:gateId="793" firstName="Mathias" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Cormann" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="776;777">Mathias Cormann</Person> has indicated the government is willing to negotiate the passage of its childcare reforms, paid for by cuts to family tax benefits. The government is keen to support families to get better quality childcare with legislation expected to be put to the parliament during the autumn session. The government plans to introduce an omnibus bill that will see lower income families better off for childcare. To pay for the changes the government will cut some family benefits, including the end of year supplement for people on Family Tax Part A and Part B. &apos;As a government we have shown we are very willing to pragmatically negotiate and we will continue to do that,&apos; <Person gate:gateId="794" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" surname="Cormann" kind="personName" rule="PersonTitleGenderUnknown" title="Senator" gate:matches="776;777">Senator Cormann</Person> told <Organization gate:gateId="795" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">ABC</Organization>. Independent <Person gate:gateId="796" firstName="Nick" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="unknown" surname="Xenophon" kind="personName" rule="PersonTitleGenderUnknown" title="Senator">Senator Nick Xenophon</Person> has told <Organization gate:gateId="797" orgType="newspaper" rule="NewspaperEndng" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Sky News</Organization> says his party will consider the changes. &apos;It depends how you structure it and that&apos;s something we will talk to all the stakeholders, including people like ACOSS, about their concerns. &apos;I also under the imperative the government has that their concerned about the Triple A credit rating, about losing that rating. &apos;And if the government doesn&apos;t get certain savings it will look at increasing taxes.&apos; Shadow childcare minister <Person gate:gateId="798" rule="PersonJobTitle" kind="fullName" ruleFinal="PersonFinal">Kate Ellis</Person> says the opposition will not support paying for the bill by stripping family tax benefits. &apos;What we cannot support and have made very clear is that we don&apos;t think that other low and middle income Australian families should have to pay this. We don&apos;t think the Family tax benefit cuts should be linked as a way of holding the parliament to ransom.&apos;