<Location gate:gateId="1827" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1762;1763;1770;1772;1791">FIJI</Location> MAKES SUGAR PAYMENT TO GET HARVEST STARTED
  <Location gate:gateId="1828" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1762;1763;1770;1772;1791">Fiji</Location> sugar farmers will receive an interim
  payment on the 1986 crop, four months ahead of schedule, in a
  move aimed at getting harvesting of the drought-hit 1987 crop
  under way, Governor-general Ratu <Person gate:gateId="1835" rule="PersonTitle1" gate:matches="1816;1817;1819;1820;1821;1822">Sir Penaia Ganilau</Person> said.
      Industry sources said latest forecasts for the 1987 crop
  indicated output of 360,000 tonnes, well down on the record
  501,800 tonne tel quel production in the 1986 (May-December)
  crop year.
      The previous record was set in 1982 when <Location gate:gateId="1829" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1762;1763;1770;1772;1791">Fiji</Location> produced
  486,790 tonnes.
      For the past month <Location gate:gateId="1830" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1762;1763;1770;1772;1791">Fiji</Location> sugar farmers have delayed
  harvesting the 1987 crop pending a response from the
  Governor-general to demands following the May 14 coup.
      <Person gate:gateId="1836" matchedWithLonger="true" rule="PersonSays" gate:matches="1816;1817;1819;1820;1821;1822">Ganilau</Person> said in a statement the <Organization gate:gateId="1831" orgType="company" rule="OrgXEnding" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1775;1788">Fiji Sugar Corp</Organization> would make
  a payment of five dlrs per tonne against the final payment for
  the 1986 crop on the understanding that preparations by growers
  for commencement of harvesting would be completed at all <Person gate:gateId="1832" firstName="mills" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="1777;1780;1818">mills</Person>
  by June 23.
      Crushing would commence at Labasa and <Location gate:gateId="1833" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Penang</Location> <Person gate:gateId="1834" rule="FirstPersonStop" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" gate:matches="1777;1780;1818" kind="firstName">mills</Person> on June
  23 and at Lautoka and <Person gate:gateId="1837" firstName="Rarawai" rule="UnknownSurname" gender="male" gate:matches="1777;1780;1818" surname="mills" kind="personName">Rarawai mills</Person> on June 30, he said.
      The interim payment, to be made on or about June 30, is the
  full amount of the grower&apos;s share of 1986 sugar proceeds
  received to-date. The balance will be paid in October.
      Growers had also called for the full 1987 forecast price of
  23.50 dlrs per tonne of cane to be paid in cash on delivery to
  the mill, but this has been rejected by the state controlled
  <Organization gate:gateId="1839" orgType="unknown" rule="OrgXEnding" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1775;1788">Fiji Sugar Corp</Organization>, <Person gate:gateId="1838" matchedWithLonger="true" rule="PersonSays" gate:matches="1816;1817;1819;1820;1821;1822">Ganilau</Person> said.
      However, in addition to the scheduled delivery payment of
  14.10 dlrs, an additional sum of 2.35 dlrs, or 10 pct of the
  forecast price, would be paid on December 15, on all cane
  harvested by November 30, he said.
      <Person gate:gateId="1840" matchedWithLonger="true" rule="PersonSays" gate:matches="1816;1817;1819;1820;1821;1822">Ganilau</Person> said, &quot;This will be at least one month in advance of
  the expected date of payment of the second payment of cane. The
  balance of the second payment will be made six weeks after the
  end of crushing.&quot;
      Another demand of <Location gate:gateId="1844" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1762;1763;1770;1772;1791">Fiji</Location>&apos;s 22,000 small farmers was that an
  estimated 14 mln dlr loan from the <Organization gate:gateId="1825" orgType="unknown" rule="TheOrgXBase" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1792;1823;1824">Fiji Development Bank</Organization> (<Organization gate:gateId="1843" rule ="OrgBracketOrg" gate:matches="1792;1823;1824" orgType ="unknown">FDB</Organization>)
  for the 1983 cane crop rehabilitation programme be written off.
  The <Organization gate:gateId="1826" rule ="AcronymOrg" gate:matches="1792;1823;1824" orgType ="unknown">FDB</Organization> rejected this request.
      <Person gate:gateId="1841" matchedWithLonger="true" rule="PersonSays" gate:matches="1816;1817;1819;1820;1821;1822">Ganilau</Person> said, however, &quot;The bank is prepared to carefully
  consider requests for rescheduling loan repayments in cases of
  hardship on a case-by-case basis.&quot;
      In response to a further demand that all soldiers be
  removed from the cane growing areas, <Person gate:gateId="1842" matchedWithLonger="true" rule="PersonSays" gate:matches="1816;1817;1819;1820;1821;1822">Ganilau</Person> said the army
  would restrict its presence in the cane areas.
      He said he had directed the authorities to issue permits to
  harvesting gangs, cane growers and sugar industry trade unions
  to hold the necessary meetings in preparation for the
  commencement of harvest.
      Senior representatives of the sugar cane growers had
  indicated a desire to commence the crush as soon as possible,
  he added.
  

