<Person gate:gateId="853" firstName="Alexandre" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Lacazette" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="826;843;844;845">Alexandre Lacazette</Person> has admitted he’s been doing his homework in a bid to adapt to English football – and the “dangerous” decision-making of match officials. The Frenchman joined <Organization gate:gateId="854" orgType="company" rule="joinOrg" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Arsenal</Organization> in the summer for a club record £52.7m after nine years at <Location gate:gateId="855" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Lyon</Location>. A clinical and prolific goalscorer in Ligue 1, questions were raised over whether the 26-year-old would be able to adjust to the physicality of the <Organization gate:gateId="856" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Premier</Organization> League. <Person gate:gateId="851" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="826;843;844;845" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Lacazette</Person> has certainly made a positive start, scoring four goals from seven games for <Location gate:gateId="857" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="830;832;834">Arsenal</Location>, but the player believes he still has much to learn. “I have not totally adapted yet, there are things that still surprise me, but I am trying,” the 26-year-old Frenchman told <Person gate:gateId="858" rule="PersonFullInitials" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" initials="SFR" surname="Sport" kind="fullName">SFR Sport</Person>. “I&apos;ve watched quite a few matches to understand English football. “I watch quite a lot of my matches with <Location gate:gateId="846" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="830;832;834">Arsenal</Location> and when I look back and see what I didn’t do right, I try to learn from it, which hopefully facilitates my progression.” <Person gate:gateId="852" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="826;843;844;845" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Lacazette</Person> also admitted that he has been taken aback by the nature of refereeing in English matches. “The refereeing decisions [still surprise me],” he said. “Sometimes I think it is a bit dangerous. “But then I see that nobody is shocked, so I tell myself it must be normal.” When it comes to learning the tricks of the English trade, <Person gate:gateId="850" rule="PersonSays" matchedWithLonger="true" gender="male" gate:matches="826;843;844;845">Lacazette</Person> said he turns to <Person gate:gateId="847" firstName="Thierry" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Henry" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="833;835">Thierry Henry</Person> – an <Location gate:gateId="848" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="830;832;834">Arsenal</Location> icon and personal hero of his. &quot;<Person gate:gateId="849" firstName="Henry" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="833;835">Henry</Person> was my idol, we talk a lot. He gives me advice, and if I have some questions I know I can count on him.&quot;