<Location gate:gateId="1032" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="991;992;996;999;1000">UGANDA</Location> PULLS OUT OF COFFEE MARKET - TRADE SOURCES
  <Location gate:gateId="1019" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="991;992;996;999;1000">Uganda</Location>&apos;s <Organization gate:gateId="1020" orgType="unknown" rule="OrgXBase" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="993;1015;1016;1017;1018">Coffee Marketing Board</Organization> (<Organization gate:gateId="1028" rule ="OrgBracketOrg" gate:matches="993;1015;1016;1017;1018" orgType ="unknown">CMB</Organization>)
  has stopped offering coffee on the international market because
  it is unhappy with current prices, coffee trade sources said.
      The board suspended offerings last week but because of its
  urgent need for cash it was not immediately clear how long it
  could sustain, the sources added.
      Hundreds of Ugandan coffee farmers and processors have been
  waiting several months for payment from the <Organization gate:gateId="1029" rule ="AcronymOrg" gate:matches="993;1015;1016;1017;1018" orgType ="unknown">CMB</Organization>, which has had
  trouble finding enough railway wagons to move the coffee to the
  Kenyan port of <Location gate:gateId="1021" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Mombasa</Location>.
      Foreign banks have contributed to the cash crisis by
  holding up remittance of <Location gate:gateId="1022" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="991;992;996;999;1000">Uganda</Location>&apos;s hard currency earnings from
  coffee exports, the government newspaper <Person gate:gateId="1026" rule="PersonSays">New Vision</Person> said.
      The banks are holding up to seven mln dlrs in coffee money
  and <Person gate:gateId="1027" rule="PersonTitle1">President Yoweri Museveni</Person> is thinking of imposing a penalty
  for such delays, it added.
      Banking sources said a third factor in the crisis was that
  commercial banks have lent the board only 77 billion shillings
  -- the equivalent of 55 mln dlrs -- for crop finance in the
  current coffee year, while the government had asked for 100
  billion.
      The <Organization gate:gateId="1030" rule ="AcronymOrg" gate:matches="993;1015;1016;1017;1018" orgType ="unknown">CMB</Organization> has 455,000 60-kg bags of coffee, about 15 pct of
  annual production, stockpiled in <Location gate:gateId="1023" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" kind="locName">Kampala</Location> awaiting shipment.
      The crop accounts for over 90 pct of <Location gate:gateId="1024" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="991;992;996;999;1000">Uganda</Location>&apos;s export
  earnings and the recent slide in prices to four-year lows is
  likely to more than offset an expected increase in production.
      <Organization gate:gateId="1031" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="993;1015;1016;1017;1018" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">CMB</Organization> officials have forecast that because the government has
  restored law and order in important growing areas, <Location gate:gateId="1025" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="991;992;996;999;1000">Uganda</Location> will
  produce over three mln bags of coffee in the year ending
  September 30, about 25 pct more than in 1985/6.
  

