<Location gate:gateId="1930" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="region" gate:matches="1879;1885;1904;1908">Amazon</Location> may be set to bring its hi-tech <Person gate:gateId="1931" rule="GazPersonFirst" firstName="till" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" kind="firstName">till</Person>-free stores to the <Location gate:gateId="1932" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1881;1883;1889">UK</Location> after registering the <Organization gate:gateId="1933" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1882;1888;1890">Amazon</Organization> Go brand name in the <Location gate:gateId="1934" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1881;1883;1889">UK</Location> last week. At the test store near <Location gate:gateId="1935" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="region" gate:matches="1879;1885;1904;1908">Amazon</Location>’s HQ in <Location gate:gateId="1936" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" kind="locName">Seattle</Location>, an app tracks customers as they walk about, recording the items they pick up and take away. The store is currently only available to company staff, but will open to shoppers from next year. The cost of purchases will be automatically billed to their account. The company has registered the <Organization gate:gateId="1937" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1882;1888;1890">Amazon</Organization> Go trademark in the <Location gate:gateId="1938" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1881;1883;1889">UK</Location> for an extensive list of potential uses, from technology, telecommunications and retail services to food and drink services and even pet food. The retailer claims the <Organization gate:gateId="1939" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1882;1888;1890">Amazon</Organization> Go store is “the world’s most advanced shopping technology” but other businesses are also trialling shop-assistant-free concepts. The Näraffär convenience store based in an isolated village in <Location gate:gateId="1940" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" kind="locName">Sweden</Location>, for example, relies on a mobile app which lets residents access the store, scan their shopping and then pay via a monthly invoice. They’re part of a wave of new gadgetry which could dramatically change the way we shop: Robot assistants. Some may argue that many stores have these already, but retailers are moving on, with a view to replacing staff with sophisticated software. The American DIY chain <Person gate:gateId="1941" rule="GazPersonFirst" firstName="Lowe" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" gate:matches="1892;1894" kind="firstName">Lowe</Person>’s is testing LoweBot, a customer service robot that speaks several languages, helps shoppers find items and provides information on products. First trialled as OSHbot two years ago, it is currently being tested in 11 <Person gate:gateId="1942" rule="GazPersonFirst" firstName="Lowe" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" gate:matches="1892;1894" kind="firstName">Lowe</Person>’s stores. <Location gate:gateId="1943" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1895;1899">US</Location> electricals retailer <Organization gate:gateId="1944" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Best Buy</Organization> has <Person gate:gateId="1945" rule="GazPersonFirst" firstName="Chloe" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" kind="firstName">Chloe</Person>, a robot that is a glorified grabber arm for CDs and DVDs, while Aldebaran Robotics, part of the Japanese telecoms firm Softbank, has created Pepper, a humanoid robot which has been deployed in some Nescafé stores in <Location gate:gateId="1946" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" kind="locName">Japan</Location>. Some <Location gate:gateId="1947" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1895;1899">US</Location> shopping centres are even adopting robotic security guards – a cross between a CCTV camera and a Dalek that can detect people who may be loitering in the wrong place and read car number plates in car parks. But it’s not all been straightforward: a robot guarding a shopping centre in <Location gate:gateId="1948" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="province" kind="locName">California</Location> recently ran over a toddler after its navigational scanning systems failed to detect the small boy. A virtual you. For many shoppers, buying clothes online is a very hit-and-miss affair. Sizes vary between outlets and getting the right fit means many clothing items are returned – which is bad for both the shopper and the shopkeeper. That could change thanks to new software that creates an accurate 3D model of the shopper, meaning it is possible to “try on” clothes. <Location gate:gateId="1949" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Cambridge</Location> based startup Metail, which has raised $20m to date and is backed by <Location gate:gateId="1950" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Hong Kong</Location> clothing giant Tal, is setting the pace. The company’s technology can be plugged into retailers’ websites so customers can create what it calls “Me Models” as well as 3D images of the products on sale. Shoppers can then find out if a pair of tight jeans will give them a muffin top. Retailers will also be able to use customer data to suggest outfits, creating a “<Organization gate:gateId="1951" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Netflix</Organization> style” shopping experience. Digital butlers. Doing the shopping may soon require nothing other than a shiny little box. Nearly all the major tech firms, including <Location gate:gateId="1952" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="region" gate:matches="1879;1885;1904;1908">Amazon</Location>, <Organization gate:gateId="1953" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Google</Organization>, <Organization gate:gateId="1954" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Apple</Organization> and <Organization gate:gateId="1955" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Facebook</Organization>, are developing digital home assistants that respond to voice commands. As an online retailer, it’s not surprising that <Location gate:gateId="1956" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="region" gate:matches="1879;1885;1904;1908">Amazon</Location> has ensured its <Person gate:gateId="1957" rule="GazPersonFirst" firstName="Echo" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" kind="firstName">Echo</Person> device is easy to shop with – thanks to the <Person gate:gateId="1958" rule="GazPersonFirst" firstName="Alexa" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" kind="firstName">Alexa</Person> app, which lets you shout out a shopping list, to add to a virtual trolley, as you walk around the house. Eventually these assistants should learn what you want and when you want it without commands. But these devices may be very shortlived – because home appliances like fridges, coffee machines and printers have already been developed that are linked to the internet so they can automatically replenish themselves without any interaction with their owner.