Fc <Location gate:gateId="613" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="584;587;590">Barcelona</Location> president Josep <Person gate:gateId="614" firstName="Maria" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" surname="Bartomeu" kind="fullName">Maria Bartomeu</Person> has admitted the club would have to discuss the possibility of leaving La Liga if Catalonia gained independence from <Location gate:gateId="615" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="586;594">Spain</Location>. There was violence in Catalonia over the weekend after police and voters clashed during the referendum, which has been deemed illegal by the central government, leading <Location gate:gateId="616" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="584;587;590">Barcelona</Location> to take the decision to play their game with <Location gate:gateId="617" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Las Palmas</Location> on Sunday night behind closed doors. Catalan’s sports minister had already said that teams like <Location gate:gateId="618" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="584;587;590">Barcelona</Location> and Espanyol would be eligible to play in <Location gate:gateId="619" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="province" kind="locName">England</Location>, <Location gate:gateId="608" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">France</Location> and <Location gate:gateId="609" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Italy</Location>, as well as <Location gate:gateId="610" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="586;594">Spain</Location>, and used teams like <Location gate:gateId="611" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Monaco</Location> and <Location gate:gateId="612" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Swansea</Location> of examples of Uefa allowing it. And Bartomeu corroborated this by admitting it would need to be talked about should the region achieve independence. “This situation does not exist so far,” he said on Monday. “But with regards to things that can happen in the future, it is something that the board of directors would discuss. It would be something to analyse calmly. “If we discuss the subject intensely then obviously we will find the best solution. But if this [independence] happens, the board of directors will see.”