<Location gate:gateId="1953" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1917;1918;1923;1925;1926;1927;1928;1932">U.S.</Location> COFFEE IMPORT REPORTING SYSTEM QUESTIONED
  A voluntary compliance system for
  monitoring <Location gate:gateId="1954" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1917;1918;1923;1925;1926;1927;1928;1932">U.S.</Location> coffee imports under quotas is viewed
  skeptically by many in the coffee industry, said analysts and
  trade sources.
      &quot;Many sectors of the trade, including large roasters and 
  importers, are adamant against voluntary compliance because of
  the past, which was subject to tremendous irregularities as it
  became a matter of the trade monitoring each other,&quot; one
  analyst said.
      On Monday, a <Organization gate:gateId="1942" orgType="unknown" rule="TheOrgXBase" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">National Coffee Association</Organization> newsletter said
  the <Organization gate:gateId="1943" orgType="unknown" rule="BaseofOrg" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Office of U</Organization>.S. Trade Representative will implement a
  voluntary compliance system temporarily because legislation to
  monitor imports is tied up in the Congressional trade bill.
      Under the arrangement, milar to one in 1980, coffee
  importers would voluntarily present needed documents to the
  <Location gate:gateId="1944" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1917;1918;1923;1925;1926;1927;1928;1932">U.S.</Location> government until <Organization gate:gateId="1945" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Congress</Organization> approves the monitoring
  authority, but if coffee arrives without valid certification,
  it will still be allowed entry.
      While many believe producers will not seek to add to the
  overburdened stock situation in the <Location gate:gateId="1946" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1917;1918;1923;1925;1926;1927;1928;1932">U.S.</Location>, others believe some
  will ship outside of the quota requirements in lieu of
  monitoring controls, trade sources said.
      &quot;Last time, there was a lot of false information submitted
  to customs which resulted in a lot of indictments and fines,&quot; a
  <Location gate:gateId="1947" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1917;1918;1923;1925;1926;1927;1928;1932">U.S.</Location> Customs spokesman said.
      &quot;Customs can do a good job when given the tools, but when
  its hands are tied, it doesn&apos;t have the authority to demand
  Form O (documents tracking merchandise from source to
  destination),&quot; he said.
      Many see it as a true test of whether producers and
  importers will abide by the quota system.
      &quot;It is a key to seeing whether there are any teeth in the
  quota agreement,&quot; said one major <Location gate:gateId="1948" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1917;1918;1923;1925;1926;1927;1928;1932">U.S.</Location> roaster.
       &quot;Last time we had a gentleman&apos;s agreement, the trade did
  not act as a gentleman,&quot; said another analyst adding, &quot;without
  the need to submit documents, the ball will be in the
  producers&apos; hands.&quot;
      Some feel that importers will take advantage of the
  voluntary compliance due to development of a two-tier market,
  in which non-member countries buy coffee at a big discount.
  Many fear that dealers will buy coffee destined for non-member
  countries at discounts and then bring it into the <Location gate:gateId="1949" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1917;1918;1923;1925;1926;1927;1928;1932">U.S.</Location> falsely
  labelled.
      According to customs officials, several green coffee
  importers confessed in 1985 that they had imported coffee
  fraudulently after buying it for non-member destinations,
  forging landing certificates and then relabelling it as navy
  beans.
      &quot;If there&apos;s that much of a discrepancy between prices for
  one country and another, producers may be teted to get rid of
  their stocks of coffee by selling to non-member nations and by
  circumventing the quota provisions,&quot; said <Organization gate:gateId="1950" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Paine Webber</Organization> analyst
  <Person gate:gateId="1951" firstName="Bernie" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Savaiko" kind="fullName">Bernie Savaiko</Person>.
      Still, others believe that producers will not be hard
  pressed to aggravate the overburdened coffee stock situation in
  the <Location gate:gateId="1952" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1917;1918;1923;1925;1926;1927;1928;1932">U.S.</Location> in the near term.
      &quot;It would be naive to suggest that any agreement would not
  have some share of connivance, but I think the voluntary system
  seemed to suffice and, coupled with the fact that we have so
  much coffee, I don&apos;t think that it poses that much of a
  threat,&quot; one trader said.
  

