<Person gate:gateId="1503" firstName="John" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Bercow" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="1458;1489;1490;1491">John Bercow</Person> spoke for <Location gate:gateId="1506" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1459;1465;1473">Britain</Location>. If the government wishes to grant a state visit to the bigoted megalomaniac who currently inhabits the <Organization gate:gateId="1507" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">White House</Organization>, that is technically its right. But the speaker has the right to intervene on who gets to address parliament. To coin a phrase, Speaker <Person gate:gateId="1502" rule="Unknown" matchedWithLonger="true" gender="male" gate:matches="1458;1489;1490;1491" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Bercow</Person> took back control. Last year’s victors in the <Organization gate:gateId="1510" orgType="other" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">EU</Organization> referendum promised parliamentary sovereignty: they cannot object when it is now exercised. Given <Person gate:gateId="1504" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1458;1489;1490;1491" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Bercow</Person>’s commendable efforts to combat sexism and racism in politics, it would have been hypocritical not to speak out. It is <Person gate:gateId="1505" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1458;1489;1490;1491" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Bercow</Person>’s reasoning – that <Person gate:gateId="1512" firstName="Donald" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Trump" kind="fullName" rule="GazPerson" gate:matches="1463;1492;1493;1494;1495;1496;1497;1498;1499">Donald Trump</Person>’s sexism, racism and attacks on the independence of the judiciary disqualify him from a parliamentary visit – that have led some to criticise the speaker for abandoning political neutrality. There is an important argument to be had here. Soon after <Person gate:gateId="1508" rule="Unknown" matchedWithLonger="true" gender="male" gate:matches="1463;1492;1493;1494;1495;1496;1497;1498;1499" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Trump</Person>’s election, a senior broadcast news producer told me of his fears about the way in which the new president would be normalised. It included muddying the water on, say, what actually constitutes racism or sexism. Rather than reporting the president’s interventions as being racist or sexist, his comments would become merely “controversial”. And as such, the most powerful man on Earth would help send the fights against discrimination of various hues hurtling back decades, because it would become harder to identify it, let alone call it out. <Person gate:gateId="1509" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1463;1492;1493;1494;1495;1496;1497;1498;1499" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Trump</Person> has spoken about women in the most derogatory terms possible, has smeared Mexican immigrants as rapists and criminals, demanded a blanket ban on Muslims, and appointed as chief strategist the former editor of a far-right website. His sexism and racism are objective facts. The sky is blue, the Earth is round, <Person gate:gateId="1511" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1463;1492;1493;1494;1495;1496;1497;1498;1499" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Trump</Person> is a racist and a sexist. When we start arguing that his racism and sexism are open to debate, that to label him as such is to compromise objectivity, we strip both words of their meaning. This is already happening. The emboldened bigots of the western world believe they can speak and act with impunity, and nobody can challenge them on it. This must stop. If <Person gate:gateId="1514" firstName="Theresa" rule="GazPerson" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" surname="May" kind="fullName">Theresa May</Person> believed that her attempts to turn <Location gate:gateId="1517" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1459;1465;1473">Britain</Location> into a client state of <Location gate:gateId="1519" rule="LocGeneralKey" kind="locName" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Trump</Location>’s <Location gate:gateId="1521" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">America</Location> would be smooth, she should have been less naive. The government is under pressure, it is on the defensive: exactly the moment to up the ante. On Thursday, the new Stop <Person gate:gateId="1513" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1463;1492;1493;1494;1495;1496;1497;1498;1499" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Trump</Person> coalition has its first open activists’ meeting to plan coming actions. When members of parliament debate <Person gate:gateId="1515" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1463;1492;1493;1494;1495;1496;1497;1498;1499" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Trump</Person>’s state visit – an honour some <Location gate:gateId="1522" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">US</Location> presidents have never received – on 20 February, they will hear the voices of thousands of protesters outside. The British government is invaluable to <Person gate:gateId="1516" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1463;1492;1493;1494;1495;1496;1497;1498;1499" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Trump</Person>: May helps to normalise and legitimise him. That the speaker of the <Organization gate:gateId="1500" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">House of Commons</Organization> called out <Person gate:gateId="1518" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1463;1492;1493;1494;1495;1496;1497;1498;1499" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Trump</Person> for what he is underlines that this is no normal president. The government didn’t have to humiliate <Location gate:gateId="1501" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="1459;1465;1473">Britain</Location> by trying to make this country <Person gate:gateId="1520" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1463;1492;1493;1494;1495;1496;1497;1498;1499" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Trump</Person>’s lapdog. It chose to, and now it is facing the consequences.