The <Organization gate:gateId="2803" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2726;2740;2775;2781">White House</Organization> has distributed a list of 78 terrorist attacks to support <Person gate:gateId="2804" firstName="Donald" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Trump" kind="fullName" rule="GazPerson" gate:matches="2727;2763;2797;2798;2800;2801">Donald Trump</Person>’s claim that the media is failing to properly report them. But the list includes many atrocities that received blanket western media coverage including the <Location gate:gateId="2805" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="2728;2747;2759">Paris</Location> Bataclan attacks, the Nice truck killings and the <Location gate:gateId="2806" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="2729;2780">San Bernardino</Location> shootings. Many others including the <Location gate:gateId="2807" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Sydney</Location> siege and <Location gate:gateId="2808" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Germany</Location>’s Christmas market attack received wide international coverage. The list also includes multiple errors and spelling mistakes, including “<Location gate:gateId="2809" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">San</Location> Bernadino”, and excludes numerous terror attacks across the <Location gate:gateId="2810" locType="region" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Middle East</Location>. The release comes after the <Location gate:gateId="2811" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="2735;2778">US</Location> president told military leaders in <Location gate:gateId="2812" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" kind="locName">Tampa</Location>, <Location gate:gateId="2813" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="province" gate:matches="2737;2746">Florida</Location>, on Monday that there have been attacks all over <Location gate:gateId="2814" locType="region" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Europe</Location> but “in many cases the very, very dishonest press doesn’t want to report it”. He added: “They have their reasons, and you understand that,” but did not expand. Later the <Organization gate:gateId="2815" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2726;2740;2775;2781">White House</Organization> press secretary, <Person gate:gateId="2816" firstName="Sean" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Spicer" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="2741;2799">Sean Spicer</Person>, was asked about specific attacks that had not been reported, to which he replied: “We’ll provide a list later. There’s several instances … There’s a lot of instances that have occurred where I don’t think they’ve gotten the coverage it deserved.” That list, released to media outlets including the Guardian, included a “timeline” of domestic and international incidents from September 2014 to December 2016. Some, such as last year’s mass shooting at the Pulse nightclub in <Location gate:gateId="2817" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" kind="locName">Orlando</Location>, <Location gate:gateId="2818" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="province" gate:matches="2737;2746">Florida</Location>, and the killing of 129 people in <Location gate:gateId="2819" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="2728;2747;2759" kind="locName">Paris</Location> in November 2015, received huge coverage. But officials claimed that “most” of the attacks were not adequately reported by western media outlets, <Organization gate:gateId="2820" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2749;2779">CNN</Organization> reported. The list hops from <Location gate:gateId="2821" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Afghanistan</Location> to <Location gate:gateId="2822" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Algeria</Location> to <Location gate:gateId="2823" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="2752;2768">Australia</Location> but, without explanation, does not mention <Location gate:gateId="2824" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Israel</Location>, where incidents included a bus bombing in <Location gate:gateId="2825" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" kind="locName">Jerusalem</Location> last year, carried out by a 19-year-old Palestinian, that injured 20 people. A December 2016 cut-off also excludes the <Location gate:gateId="2826" rule="LocationPost" kind="locName" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Québec City</Location> mosque attack from the list, an attack <Person gate:gateId="2848" rule="Unknown" matchedWithLonger="true" gender="male" gate:matches="2727;2763;2797;2798;2800;2801" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Trump</Person> was publicly silent about, despite condemning on <Organization gate:gateId="2827" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Twitter</Organization> the Louvre attack in <Location gate:gateId="2828" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="2728;2747;2759" kind="locName">Paris</Location> several days later. The murder of British backpacker <Person gate:gateId="2829" firstName="Mia" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" surname="Ayliffe-Chung" kind="fullName">Mia Ayliffe-Chung</Person> in an Australian hostel last year was also included on the list, even though extremism had been ruled out as a motive by both police and the victim’s mother. In an open letter to <Person gate:gateId="2849" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="2727;2763;2797;2798;2800;2801" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Trump</Person>, <Person gate:gateId="2830" firstName="Rosie" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" surname="Ayliffe" kind="fullName">Rosie Ayliffe</Person> accused <Person gate:gateId="2831" firstName="Donald" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Trump" kind="fullName" rule="GazPerson" gate:matches="2727;2763;2797;2798;2800;2801">Donald Trump</Person> of using “fake news” about her daughter’s death to further the “persecution of innocent people” by falsely claiming she was the victim of a terrorist attack. “My daughter’s death will not be used to further this insane persecution of innocent people,” she wrote. The document also includes spelling mistakes such as “attaker” instead of “attacker” and “Denmakr” instead of “<Location gate:gateId="2832" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Denmark</Location>”. There have been similar errors in official communications in recent days, including references to <Person gate:gateId="2833" firstName="Theresa" rule="GazPerson" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" surname="May" kind="fullName">Theresa May</Person> as “<Person gate:gateId="2834" rule="GazPersonFirst" firstName="Teresa" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" kind="firstName">Teresa</Person>” and a reference to <Person gate:gateId="2835" firstName="Malcolm" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Turnbull" kind="fullName">Malcolm Turnbull</Person> as the “president” of <Location gate:gateId="2836" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="2752;2768">Australia</Location> when it should be “prime minister”. The catalogue begins with an attack by <Person gate:gateId="2837" firstName="Abdul" rule="PersonFullDoubleBarrelled" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Haider" kind="fullName">Abdul Numan Haider</Person>, who wounded two police officers in a knife attack in <Location gate:gateId="2838" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" kind="locName">Melbourne</Location> in September 2014. It ends with an atrocity involving Anis Amri, who drove a truck into a crowded market in <Location gate:gateId="2839" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" kind="locName">Berlin</Location> last December, killing 12 and injuring 48. <Person gate:gateId="2840" firstName="Lindsay" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="female" surname="Walters" kind="fullName">Lindsay Walters</Person>, a <Organization gate:gateId="2841" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2726;2740;2775;2781">White House</Organization> spokesperson, claimed that the list demonstrates how terrorist attacks are losing perceived news value because of their frequency. “The real point here is that these terrorists attacks are so pervasive at this point that they do not spark the wall-to-wall coverage they once did,” she said via email. “If you look back just a few years ago, any one of these attacks would have been ubiquitous in every news outlet, and now they’re happening so often – at a rate of more than once every two weeks, according to the list – that networks are not devoting to each of them the same level of coverage they once did. “This cannot be allowed to become the ‘new normal’, and the President, for one, is not going to be satisfied until the American people are much safer and more secure.” Earlier, <Person gate:gateId="2850" rule="Unknown" matchedWithLonger="true" gender="male" gate:matches="2741;2799" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Spicer</Person> told reporters travelling on <Organization gate:gateId="2842" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Air Force</Organization> One that <Person gate:gateId="2851" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="2727;2763;2797;2798;2800;2801" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Trump</Person> believes attacks are not “unreported” but “under-reported”. He said: “He felt members of the media don’t always cover some of those events to the extent that other events might get covered.” But <Person gate:gateId="2843" firstName="David" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Gergen" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="2777;2802">David Gergen</Person>, a political analyst and former adviser to four <Location gate:gateId="2844" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="2735;2778">US</Location> presidents, condemned <Person gate:gateId="2852" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="2727;2763;2797;2798;2800;2801" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Trump</Person>’s remarks. “I think this is one of the most outrageous claims the president has made, among many, because it really says, basically, that the press is not doing its job because it has its own political agenda,” he told <Organization gate:gateId="2845" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2749;2779">CNN</Organization>. “It doesn’t want you to know the truth about how dangerous terrorism is. It doesn’t want to be out there, it’s just pulling a leftist agenda on you, which is clearly not true.” <Person gate:gateId="2853" rule="Unknown" matchedWithLonger="true" gender="male" gate:matches="2777;2802" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Gergen</Person> added: “He engages in these falsehoods without producing any serious evidence. The list includes <Location gate:gateId="2846" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="2729;2780">San Bernardino</Location>, as if the press didn’t cover that sufficiently. It’s just astonishing and it’s beneath the dignity of the presidency and I think it tears at the fabric of what holds us together as a people when we can’t trust each other, we can’t trust the <Organization gate:gateId="2847" orgType="government" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2726;2740;2775;2781">White House</Organization>, and he’s telling us we can’t trust the press. This is the way democracies come unravelled.”