Usain <Person gate:gateId="1058" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1045;1046;1047;1048;1050;1051;1052" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Bolt</Person> is closer to achieving his lifelong ambition of becoming a professional footballer after agreeing to train with Borussia Dortmund. The nine-time Olympic gold medallist has made no secret of his desire to swap spikes for studs ever since establishing himself as history’s greatest-ever sprinter. Now, in an interview with <Organization gate:gateId="1053" orgType="newspaper" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1010;1018">The Guardian</Organization>, <Person gate:gateId="1060" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1045;1046;1047;1048;1050;1051;1052" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Bolt</Person> has claimed that he and his representatives have “genuinely been talking to people” about the possibility of transitioning to football after retiring from athletics. The interview reveals that <Person gate:gateId="1061" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1045;1046;1047;1048;1050;1051;1052" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Bolt</Person> has been in touch with <Person gate:gateId="1054" firstName="Thomas" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Tuchel" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="1011;1049">Thomas Tuchel</Person>, the Dortmund head coach, who agreed to let him train with the Bundesliga club. The 30-year-old Jamaican wishes to “see what happens” once he has worked with <Person gate:gateId="1063" rule="Unknown" matchedWithLonger="true" gender="male" gate:matches="1011;1049" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Tuchel</Person>, but has his eyes set on a move to <Location gate:gateId="1055" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="1012;1017">Manchester</Location> United, the club he supports. <Person gate:gateId="1066" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1045;1046;1047;1048;1050;1051;1052" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Bolt</Person> has talked up a move to Old Trafford in the past and was the club’s guest of honour for a <Organization gate:gateId="1056" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Premier</Organization> League clash with <Location gate:gateId="1059" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Fulham</Location> in 2012 following his success at the <Location gate:gateId="1062" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">London</Location> Olympics. “For me, if I could get to play for <Location gate:gateId="1064" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="city" gate:matches="1012;1017">Manchester</Location> United, that would be like a dream come true,” he told <Organization gate:gateId="1065" orgType="newspaper" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="1010;1018">The Guardian</Organization>. “Yes, that would be epic.” Last year, <Person gate:gateId="1067" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1045;1046;1047;1048;1050;1051;1052" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Bolt</Person> claimed that he was good enough to at least be offered a trial by United, insisting: “I am fit, I am quick, I can control the ball and I understand all of the play. “I think if I do a trial then they would say, &apos;You know what, here is a contract for five years! You are 30 years old, here&apos;s a five-year contract. Let&apos;s just do it!’,” he told MUTV. <Person gate:gateId="1069" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="1045;1046;1047;1048;1050;1051;1052" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Bolt</Person> welcomed the appointment of <Person gate:gateId="1068" firstName="Jose" rule="PersonFull" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Mourinho" kind="fullName">Jose Mourinho</Person> as United’s manager earlier this year and, once again, claimed he deserved a chance to play under the Portuguese. &quot;I haven&apos;t got the call yet, but I know it&apos;s coming. I think he&apos;s waiting until after the Olympics,&quot; <Person gate:gateId="1057" rule="PersonSays" gate:matches="1045;1046;1047;1048;1050;1051;1052">Bolt</Person> said in July.