<Person gate:gateId="2275" firstName="Lewis" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Hamilton" kind="fullName" rule="PersonLocAmbig" gate:matches="2174;2176;2179;2181;2184;2186;2191;2192;2193">Lewis Hamilton</Person> has said there will be no let-up in his drive to claim a fourth Formula One world championship as the season enters the final five meetings at the Japanese Grand Prix this weekend. The British driver was insistent that his battle with Ferrari’s <Person gate:gateId="2276" firstName="Sebastian" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" surname="Vettel" kind="fullName" rule="PersonFull" gate:matches="2175;2221;2222;2223;2224;2225">Sebastian Vettel</Person> would remain fiercely competitive and that he would “prepare for war”. <Person gate:gateId="2252" firstName="Hamilton" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="2174;2176;2179;2181;2184;2186;2191;2192;2193">Hamilton</Person> leads <Person gate:gateId="2270" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="2175;2221;2222;2223;2224;2225" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Vettel</Person> by 34 points after he claimed second place at the last round in <Location gate:gateId="2253" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="2178;2182;2196" kind="locName">Malaysia</Location> while <Person gate:gateId="2271" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="2175;2221;2222;2223;2224;2225" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Vettel</Person>, who had started at the back of the grid, could manage only fourth. <Person gate:gateId="2254" firstName="Hamilton" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="2174;2176;2179;2181;2184;2186;2191;2192;2193">Hamilton</Person>, who had struggled with his car in Sepang with the <Organization gate:gateId="2255" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2180;2194">Mercedes</Organization> proving difficult to set up and lacking the pace of both the Red Bulls and Ferraris, was under no illusions of what he had to do to maintain the advantage. “I’ve got to make sure I’m fit, healthy, focused,” the British driver said. “Basically prepare for war. That’s what I try and do, make sure every weekend I’m the best prepared I can be.” <Person gate:gateId="2256" firstName="Hamilton" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="2174;2176;2179;2181;2184;2186;2191;2192;2193">Hamilton</Person> had trailed <Person gate:gateId="2272" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="2175;2221;2222;2223;2224;2225" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Vettel</Person> in the title race until Monza but he has now won four of the past five races and seven this season. <Person gate:gateId="2273" rule="Unknown" matchedWithLonger="true" gender="male" gate:matches="2175;2221;2222;2223;2224;2225" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Vettel</Person> has four victories but the Ferrari was quicker at the past two rounds and displayed a marked improvement in pace after an engine upgrade in <Location gate:gateId="2257" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="2178;2182;2196" kind="locName">Malaysia</Location>. He dropped points after going out in a first-lap crash in <Location gate:gateId="2258" rule="InLoc1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="2183;2197" kind="locName">Singapore</Location> and the grid penalty at Sepang. If <Person gate:gateId="2259" firstName="Hamilton" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="2174;2176;2179;2181;2184;2186;2191;2192;2193">Hamilton</Person> leaves <Location gate:gateId="2260" locType="country" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Japan</Location> with a 28-point gap over <Person gate:gateId="2274" rule="Unknown" gate:matches="2175;2221;2222;2223;2224;2225" NMRule="Unknown" kind="PN">Vettel</Person> he can afford to finish second at the remaining races and still take the title. But he and his team, who are still having to work at how best to manage their car at different circuits and under differing conditions, were aware they could take nothing for granted. “The goal is to continue to win races even if I don’t have to,” he said. “I’m still hunting it, I’m not defending it, I’m still hunting, I’m still chasing. Until that last flag, until I’ve actually got it, you’ve got to keep pushing as hard as you can. I don’t foresee any of the coming races being easy, we need to stay on our toes as it can still be lost.” Certainly he will be confident in his own ability to master the unforgiving test of Suzuka. The track rewards precision and commitment, both of which characterise <Person gate:gateId="2261" firstName="Hamilton" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="2174;2176;2179;2181;2184;2186;2191;2192;2193">Hamilton</Person>’s style, if he is comfortable he has the car he requires, although that is not reflected in his record at Suzuka – where he has won only twice before, in 2014 and 2015. One of the finest moments of his career was at the Japanese Grand Prix when it was held at <Organization gate:gateId="2262" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal">Fuji</Organization> Speedway in 2007. He won there in terrible conditions and has described it as one of his five best races. Unsurprisingly, his performance won him a lot of Japanese supporters. <Person gate:gateId="2263" firstName="Hamilton" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="2174;2176;2179;2181;2184;2186;2191;2192;2193">Hamilton</Person> is certainly not lacking support here. The home fans were out in force – with several thousand in the main grandstand alone, on a day when no cars are on track. Alongside the usual array of detailed home-made headwear – including rear wings, with working DRS lovingly attached to some crash hats – was a swathe of union flags emblazoned with messages of support for <Person gate:gateId="2264" firstName="Hamilton" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="2174;2176;2179;2181;2184;2186;2191;2192;2193">Hamilton</Person> and he expressed gratitude for the encouragement. However, the Englishman’s focus remained firmly on claiming the title by earning it. “I don’t want to rely on fortune from the others’ misfortune,” <Person gate:gateId="2265" firstName="Hamilton" ruleFinal="PersonFinal" gender="male" matchedWithLonger="true" kind="firstName" rule="GazPersonFirst" gate:matches="2174;2176;2179;2181;2184;2186;2191;2192;2193">Hamilton</Person> said. “Ultimately if it’s on personal performance from Sebastian, I’m not bothered about that.” The key factor that could remain decisive in the championship was whether <Organization gate:gateId="2266" orgType="company" rule="GazOrganization" ruleFinal="OrgFinal" gate:matches="2180;2194">Mercedes</Organization> could master the demanding requirements of their car for the remaining rounds. “I’m confident in the car, confident in it working at some stages,” he said. “Just still this deep into the season I have no idea where it’s gonna be good, where it’s gonna be great like <Location gate:gateId="2267" locType="city" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal">Silverstone</Location> or where it’ll be a real struggle like <Location gate:gateId="2268" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="2178;2182;2196">Malaysia</Location> or <Location gate:gateId="2269" rule="Location1" ruleFinal="LocFinal" locType="country" gate:matches="2183;2197">Singapore</Location>. “That’s the exciting thing. If we were going into the race beyond this and knew what was going to happen it would be kind of dull. I like that I’m arriving and I don’t know.”
